The new מסכת masechet. *Masechet*, ערכין erachin *Arachin* or ערכין Erchin *Erchin*
they call it. This is based on the פסוקים *psukim* at the
end of בחקתי *Bechukotai*.
And actually, the next מסכת *Masechet* after ערכין *Arachin* is תמורה temurah.
*Tmura*, and both of those are at the end of בחקתי *Bechukotai*
because it says there in פרק Perek כז *Perek Chaf Zayin*, וידבר
ה׳ אל משה לאמר *Vayedaber Hashem el Moshe lemor*, דבר אל בני
ישראל ואמרת אליהם *Daber el bnei Yisrael ve'amarta aleihem*, איש כי יפלא
נדר בערכך Neder b'erkecha, נפשת לה׳ *Ish ki yaflie neder be'erkecha nefashot
l'Hashem*. If a person makes a vow of the evaluation of souls
to God, והיה ערכך הזכר *vehaya erkecha hazachar*, so if it's a
male that he is vowing of to give that person's value, מבן
עשרים שנה ועד בן ששים שנה *miben esrim shana ve'ad ben shishim
shana*, from 20 to 60, it's חמשים שקל shekel, כסף בשקל הקדש
*chamishim shekel kesef beshekel hakodesh*, 50 shekel, which is 10 times that
of a בכור *bechor*. And if it's a female, ואם ve'im, נקבה
*ve'im nekeva*, then it's 30 shekel. And if he's only five years
old to 20, it's different. So going through a whole range of
ages and based on male or female, what is the vow? And
the smallest value I should say is ואם ve'im מבן חדש *ve'im
miben chodesh*. And
so it starts from one month up, it divides different categories. The
last category is 60 plus. So whoa, so that's the, I suppose
that's the age of retirement or something in the תורה Torah *Torah*.
But anyway, so it goes from a month to five years, and
it has all of these different values. That is ערכין *Arachin*. And
then the next
פרשה parsha *parsha* right in the תורה Torah *Torah* just to mention
is ואם בהמה אשר יקריבו ממנה קרבן korban. לה׳ *ve'im behema asher
yakrivu mimenu korban l'Hashem*, כל אשר יתן ממנו לה׳ יהיה קדש *kol
asher yiten mimenu l'Hashem yihiye kodesh*, לא lo יחליפנו ולא ימיר yamir,
אתו טוב ברע או רע בטוב *lo yachalifenu velo yamir oto tov
bera o ra betov*, ואם המר ימיר בהמה בבהמה והיה הוא ותמורתו
יהיה קדש *ve'im hamer yamir behema bivehema vehaya hu utmurato yihiye kodesh*.
So in the תורה Torah *Torah* itself you have ערכין *Arachin* and
then תמורה temurah *Tmura*, and here we have it the same as
well, although normally the מסכתות *Masechtot* are really arranged based on, you
know, number of פרקים *prakim* and size. Nevertheless, it works out very
nicely that we have reflecting exactly the order of the פסוקים *psukim*
in the תורה Torah, *Torah*. So this is in קדשים Kodashim. *Kodshim*
of course because it is relating to sanctifying things and making them
קדוש *kadosh*. Although here, you do not actually make the object קדוש
*kadosh*, you accept upon yourself an obligation to give a certain amount
of money to the בית המקדש Beit HaMikdash. *Beit HaMikdash*. But nevertheless,
it is relating to aspects relating to the בית המקדש Beis Hamikdash
*Beit HaMikdash* and therefore it is in this מסכת *Masechet*. So let's
in this סדר Seder *Seder*. So let's take a look. Beginning דף
ב עמוד א *Daf Bet Amud Aleph*. הכל מעריכין hakol maarichin. ונערכין
ve-ne-erachin, *Hakol maarichin vene'erachin*. All people can be מעריך maarik, *maarich*, can
do this act of ערך erech *erech*, make a vow to obligate
themselves to pay the value of a person based on those charts
in the תורה torah *Torah* as it were. ונערכין *Vene'erachin*, they can
be the object of the vow, meaning somebody can say about any
person that I will pay their value. So any person can make
the vow or be the object of the vow. נודרין ונידרין nodrin
v'nidrin, *Nodrin venidrin*. Can make a נדר neder, *neder* and to be
the object of a נדר neder *neder*. Now a נדר neder *neder*
is and often this is referred to as דמים damim *damim* versus
ערך erech. *erech*. If I say I pay, I take a vow
to take that person's value to the בית המקדש Beis Hamikdash, *Beit
HaMikdash*, that is a נדר neder. *neder* and that's called דמים damim,
*damim*, it's a value. And how do you determine value? Well, the
standard way in הלכה halachic *Halacha* we determine the value of a
person, this is not if somebody is injured or whatever, it's an
aspect but not obviously the whole aspect of it, the whole point
of it. But anyway, the normal way you assign a value to
a human being, how could you do that? Is the only place
in which human beings are assigned values is in the slave market.
So you actually determine how much that person would go as a
slave. So I should just mention, I should qualify that that if
a person is let's say injured as a result, you know, in
the normal course, right, you would in secular court, right, you would
determine, you know, pain and suffering and loss of livelihood and so
on. So that all of that is part of הלכה halachah *Halacha*
as well. Meaning הלכה halacha *Halacha* if somebody is injured, there's something
called צער *tza'ar*, which is pain and suffering, בושת *boshet*, embarrassment, you
know, ריפוי *ripuy*, doctor's bills, שבת *shevet*, loss of work, or loss
of work while the person is recuperating. And in addition to all
of that you pay for it. How do you determine in addition
to all of those derivative costs, you know, or secondary costs, how
do you determine the actual loss of the arm itself? And there
you again use this sort of slave market valuation, which we all
sort of know is not a true way to assign a value
to something, but that's the best model that we have. But my
point is that when it comes to things like injury, it's not
the only way we determine the loss, it's a tiny piece of
that. Anyway, so if somebody says the value of somebody and doesn't
use the magic word ערך erech. *erech*, if you use the word
ערך erech, *erech*, it means the fixed value assigned in the תורה
*Torah*. But if you just say the value, דמיו עלי *damav alai*,
his cost, his value, I have to pay, that is called a
נדר neder, *neder* or דמים damim *damim* and that goes by the
slave market. So that says הכל ha-kol, נודרין ונידרין *hakol nodrin venidrin*.
Anybody can make that vow and anybody can be the object of
the vow. Now we'll see how much anybody really needs anybody in
a minute. Okay, so כהנים Kohanim, *Kohanim*, here's the first anybody that
is included by that. כהנים לויים Levi'im, ישראלים ונשים *Kohanim, Levi'im, Yisre'elim,
venashim*. Whether כהן *Kohen*, לוי *Levi*, or ישראל *Yisrael*, and נשים *nashim*,
excuse me, נשים ועבדים *nashim va'avadim*, women and slaves, none of those
are excluded. Now, the problem with this list is you have to
sort of know how to read it because... where does the period
start and the next sentence begin. But it's clear from context that
there is a period, and then it says טומטום tumtum ואנדרוגינוס, right,
those the people that are טומטום tumtum is somebody that you his
genitalia or genitalia are covered up, you don't know if it's male
female, אנדרוגינוס androgynos is somebody has both genitalia. So what's their story?
Those are an exception. נודרים ונידרים, nodrin ve-nidrin, they can take vows
and be the object of vows, but still, you'd you'd obligate yourself
to pay somebody's value, doesn't matter if you're male, female, or somewhere
in between. You could also be the object of that vow, whatever
that person's cost is in the slave market. Fine. ומעריכין, u-maarikin, and
they can also obligate themselves in the ערך erech. of a person.
But אבל לא נערכין, aval lo ne-erachin, they cannot be the object
of an ערך. erech Why? שאינו נערך אלא הזכר ודאי והנקבה ודאית.
she-eino ne-erach ela ha-zachar vadai ve-ha-nekeivah vadait. The Torah gives a chart,
here's what you pay for male, here's what you pay for female.
We don't know which column they fall in. Now you might say,
okay, but at least pay the minimum, or maybe the opposite, say
play it safe, play them pay the maximum, maybe you're oblig- maybe
they're male and maybe a male is always higher on that chart
than female, and maybe you have to pay more. So no, we
don't say that. We say the chart is only for definite males
and definite females, and a טומטום tumtum and אנדרוגינוס androgynos is not
on the chart. So you actually pay nothing if they are the
object of an ערך. erech חרש שוטה וקטן, cheresh shoteh ve-katan, how
about a חרש שוטה וקטן? cheresh shoteh ve-katan? נידרין, nidrin, you can
make they can be the object of a vow, ונערכין, and the
object of an ערך, erech, because they have a because they have
a value in the slave market and because they're on the charts,
male female based on age. אבל לא נודרין, aval lo nodrin, they
cannot be the subject, they cannot make a נדר, neder. ולא מעריכין,
ve-lo maarikin, or make an ערך. Erech Why? מפני שאין בהם דעת.
mipnei she-ein bahem daat. These are the this is the classic trio
that we say cannot do legally binding actions. So the same way
they can't engage in let's say financial transactions or other types of
legally binding effects of מצוות, mitzvot, in general they're not yet of
the age of majority, so they cannot yet do legally binding actions.
So they cannot also take these vows to obligate themselves. Yes, and
an עבד כנעני... eved Kenaani...
okay. Right, so the he would not he would have the debt,
outstanding debt, and he wouldn't pay until he either was freed, or
somebody actually gave him property on the stipulation that it didn't it's
his that his owner did not take possession of it, which it's
possible to do. So, but even if he did not have any
any assets now, he would have it as an outstanding debt until
he actually was freed, if and when he would eventually become free
and have assets. So let's take a look at the גמרא. Gemara.
הכל מעריכין לאתויי מאי? ha-kol maarikin le-atuyei mai? So now the גמרא,
Gemara, because it's הכל, ha-kol, the גמרא Gemara is going to first
of all analyze what הכל, ha-kol because גמרא Gemara always assumes that
הכל ha-kol is coming to say more than everything I've just said,
it inclu- it's more inclusive. So how הכל ha-kol includes more things
in all these four four categories: מעריך, maarik. נערך, ne-erach, נודר, noder,
and נידר. nidar. And then by the way, once we get done
with that and our משנה Mishnah and figure out how הכל ha-kol
includes four different things for those four categories, we're going to talk
about הכלs ha-kol throughout ש"ס. Shas. So it's going to be a
very fun little survey of משניות mishnayot in different categories in ש"ס
Shas that use the phrase הכל hakol, to see what are they
including. So let's take a look. So it says הכל מעריכין לאתויי
מאי? ha-kol maarikin le-atuyei mai? What does that include? All people can
do the can be the subjects, can be מעריך. maarich
לאתויי מופלא סמוך לאיש. le-atuyei mufla samuch le-ish. Now this is interesting
because this actually limits the line at the end which says minors
are excluded. There is a הלכה category of when it comes to
הפלאה. haflaah. Now on the one hand as I said ערכין belongs
in our
and in our סדר of קדשים. But it also belongs in a
different
categorization. And this is a categorization the רמב"ם Rambam gives for a
number of different things called there's a one of the רמב"ם's Rambam
fourteen books is called הפלאה. Haflaah. הפלאה Haflaah
is a term which means sort of like a speech act, but
a speech act that specifically creates some sense of a of a
of an obligation. It it's almost like of a metaphysical, I don't
want to I'm trying to avoid the use of metaphysical, but it
it either sanctifies something or creates an obligation on a person, but
it's different than let's say a verbal promise. Okay, a verbal promise
is just I've committed to doing something, anyway verbal promise is not
really binding in הלכה in a legal sense. But what it does
is it actually creates some metaphysical status. So my words can sanctify
an animal. That's הפלאה. haflaah. My words can turn me into a
נזיר, nazir, if I say הריני נזיר. hareini nazir. My words can
be a נדר Neder and can make and can make fruit or
food forbidden to me. It can make me forbidden to benefit from
somebody else's things. It can create the status of forbidden and permissible.
I guess that's why it's different than let's say
a civil aspect. It actually works in the realm of sanctified, forbidden,
and and things that are sanctified, things that are forbidden. So one
of the things or things that are, you know, I guess obligations
to God as well, because one thing I can do is I
can also make a נדר Neder that I will pay certain money
to the בית המקדש. Beit HaMikdash. There's even questions... There's even questions
about when you vow to give צדקה, tzedakah, how does that fit
factor in? Okay, so that's also considered a נדר. Neder So when
I say I מעריך maarich this individual, this individual's ערך Erech is
I'm or this individual's דמים damim? is I'm it's a נדר, Neder,
that is in the category of הפלאה, hafla'ah, of a verbal act
that created this religious obligation.
That so now, why is that relevant? Because within that category of
הפלאה, hafla'ah,
the word by the way might mean enunciate, but it's taken from
the פסוק pasuk of איש כי יפלי לנדור נדר נזיר להזיר להשם,
ish ki yafli lindor neder nazir lehazir l'Hashem, what it says by
a נזיר, nazir, if a man
enunciates to make a vow of נזירות. neziros. So that word הפלאה
hafla'ah is about a verbal act that creates this religious obligation or
religious or קדושה kedushah status. So the חז"ל Chazal learn out that
within that category of הפלאה, hafla'ah, it's not limited to people that
are of the age of majority, the boys that are thirteen and
girls that are twelve, but actually can begin a year earlier. Once
a boy turns twelve years old and one day, he's in his
thirteenth year, or a girl turns eleven years old and one day,
if we determine that they understand the meaning of their words, they
understand what the vow is, they understand that it relates to God
and to the religious sphere, then it actually is binding upon them.
Now, exactly what, yeah, so we learn out, I mean it's mostly,
it's mostly, let me see if I can quote
the
פסוק. pasuk. He doesn't quote the פסוק. pasuk. But I think it's
learned from יפלי, yafli, but I'm not, I don't remember off the
top of my head the exact דרשה, drasha, but that is learned
that that is a, that that is a binding category and it's
presumably a דאורייתא d'Oraisa category. Now you might say what's the נפקא
מינה, nafka mina, you can't punish them? But there still is a
נפקא מינה. nafka mina. If he sanctifies something, it's a קרבן. korban
If he makes himself a נזיר, nazir, even if he can't be
punished necessarily, there's consequences of those acts of הפלאה, hafla'ah, those have
real world consequences beyond just whether the person can be held liable.
Okay, so that is the category of מופלא סמוך לאיש. mufla samuch
l'ish. Somebody that can be מפליא, mafli, that can make a verbal
הפלאה hafla'ah even a year before they are בר bar or בת
מצווה. bas mitzvah. So that the גמרא Gemara is saying is implicit
in this word of הכל hakol מעריכין. לאתויי מאי? l'asuyei mai? לאתויי
מופלא, l'asuyei mufla, the category of מופלא mufla when he can do
this act of verbal of הפלאה hafla'ah even if he is only
a year before being a בר bar or בת מצווה. bas mitzvah.
Yes, Reuven? Even if it's a matter of דעת daas and understanding
what you do, then why can't it be even earlier than that?
If you know who it is, you know, that's part of the
הלכה למשה מסיני halacha l'Moshe miSinai or whatever, you know, how we
learn this out. It's not, it's not purely contextual, it's not purely
based on, based on your knowledge or ability. It's based on, you
know, within the הלכה the same way the age of majority is
not that we test each individual. Here it is some balance between
an objective age, to a large degree they're already mature, but they're
not yet, and so it's, it's some combination of the objective and
the and the subjective. And maybe address this when you were mentioning
that, you know, why would you think כהנים, לויים, וישראלים? v'Yisraelim? Oh,
that I did not address actually, I don't know. Okay, so just
for the sake of saying הכל, hakol I don't know. Yes? If
this includes the person, why if we're allowing מופלא, mufla, why can't
we allow? No, so we allow מופלא mufla to do the act
of making a ערך Erech. or a נדר. Neder The subject, the
mixed gender also can be a מעריך or נודר. noder. He just
can't be the object of such because the
תורה defines, or the object, well if you say the value, meaning
the דמים, damim, the value, like the market value, then they are,
they are נידרים. nidarin. The only thing they're not is נערכים ne'erachin
because there the תורה assigns fixed values based on male-female and the
גמרא, Gemara, at least here, understands or the משנה Mishnah understands that
that's only for a clearly identified male or female. Now, certainly טומטום
tumtum is more of an interesting question because אנדרוגינוס androgynos you could
say is neither here, neither one nor the other, clearly off the
charts. So טומטום tumtum. you could say is on the charts, we
just don't know which, which one to put him in, it's our
lack of understanding. So we'll see, that is always a question about
how to deal with טומטום. Okay, but it's only the issue there
is only about the נערכים ne'erachin because the תורה has a fixed
value based on male-female. It kind of implies that they don't have
much of a value. No, because again, the standard valuation is, is
the slave market valuation, which also isn't a fair valuation, but whatever.
That's sort of the standard way we think about the value and,
you know, that's the market's assigned value, that's not like an arbitrary
value in the תורה, and that they are in that category. They
are נידרים. nidarin. So that's the market valuation, that they are in.
Can you give more, could you give both the male and the
female value for one? Well, that's what you would have thought, if
it weren't for this משנה, Mishnah, you would have thought just play
it safe, just give the bigger one and you're, but the משנה
Mishnah says, just give the bigger. All right, fine, let's keep on
going. All right, we'll see all of this. Let's keep on going.
So נערכים לאתויי מאי? ne'erachin l'asuyei mai? When it says all can
be נערך, ne'erach, the object of an ערך, Erech. what does that
include? לאתויי l'asuyei and here you get something like, you know, what
Rivka was referring to, whatever, מנוול ומוכה שחין, menuval u'mukei shachin, somebody
that, let's say, is, this is the phrase in the גמרא Gemara
which is disgusted and covered with like blisters, meaning somebody that is
has absolute, nobody would ever want this person as a slave, they
are completely, you know. can't do any job, nobody wants this person
anywhere around them, so they have no market value as a slave.
Not as a human being I hope, but as a slave they
have no market value. So therefore, since they're not in the category
of נדרים, Nedarim, of being an object of a נדר Neder because
they have a zero market value, סלקא דעתך אמינא, Salka da'atach amina,
I would have thought נדר Neder בערכך, b'erkecha? when it mentions ערך
Erech it also speaks about
vowing. So כל שישנו בדמים, Kol sheyeshno b'damim, if it's in the
category of market value which is נדר Neder by itself, ישנו בערכין,
yeshno b'erchin, then it's in the category of the ערך Erech of
the fixed values of the Torah if you use the word
ערך. Erech, וכל שאינו בדמים, V'chol she'eino b'damim, if there's no market
value to this person, אינו בערכין, eino b'erchin, then maybe it doesn't
get placed on that chart. קא משמע לן, Ka mashma lan, נפשות,
Nefashot, כל דהו, kol dehu, it says בערכך נפשות, b'erkecha nefashot, any
person. It doesn't matter whether they have a market, whether the market
gives them a value or not, any person is on this chart.
Except not any person as we know because you have to be
a definite male or definite female. What's the פשט pshat of בערכך?
It says, it says כי יפליא ki yafli the פסוק pasuk that
begins ערכין says נדר בערכך נפשות להשם. Neder b'erkecha nefashot l'Hashem. So
therefore it has juxtaposes נדר Neder and ערך. Erech, An ערך Erech.
is made through a נדר, Neder but נדר Neder by itself without
the word ערך erech, just means obligating yourself in the value. Okay.
And then somehow כל שישנו בדמים ישנו בערכין. kol sheyeshno b'damim yeshno
b'erchin.
Yeah. So which is, I'm sorry, you're saying it means that דמים
damim means market value. How does נדר Neder. mean דמים? damim, Because
נדר Neder by itself in the משנה Mishnaic terminology, נודרין ונידרין, נדר
Neder. means an obligate to pay the value, not the fixed value
of the Torah, the ערך, erech but the market value. So we're
reading that back in like fruit? No, no, right, we're talking about
a נדר Neder to pay the person's value. That's the context here.
But no מוכסין mochsin are usually buying 90-year-old slaves either, so alright,
so you could have had that as an הוה אמינא hava amina
as well. Alright, let's keep on going.
נודרין להסגויי מאי? Nodrin l'asguyei mai? Everybody can make a נדר again
in the נדר in the context of obligating yourself to pay somebody's
market value. What does that include? So the גמרא Gemara says you're
right, that doesn't include anything. But נידרין איצטריכא ליה. nidrin itztricha leh.
We had to say everybody because not to say נודר noder that
there's nothing left to say, so we already mentioned people that are
almost בר מצוה, bar mitzvah, but we said everybody to include everybody
can be the object of a נדר. So נידרין להסגויי מאי? nidrin
l'asguyei mai? Fine, so what's that coming to include? אי להסגויי טומטום
ואנדרוגינוס, Ei l'asguyei tumtum v'androgynos, somebody of mixed or indeterminate gender, that
they can be the object of a נדר because they have a
market value? בהדיא קתני לה, Behedya katani lah, that's explicit in the
משנה. Mishna. The משנה Mishna explicitly said that they're, that they can
have a market, that they have a market value and can be
the object of a נדר. ואי להסגויי חרש שוטה וקטן, V'ei l'asguyei
cheresh shoteh v'katan, how about, you know, minor and a deaf-mute and
a minor and somebody who is not of right mind? So, you
know, maybe you would think that they, because they're not adult or
because they're not of, you know, of sound, of legal majority or
of legal, you know, דעת, da'at, that maybe they're not in the
category? No, בהדיא קתני לה, behedya katani lah, it says explicit in
the משנה Mishna that they can't do the act of נדר and
the act of ערך, but they can be the object of it
because they do have a market value. So ואי להסגויי, V'ei l'asguyei,
so the גמרא Gemara says, ואי להסגויי פחות מבן חודש, v'ei l'asguyei
pachot miben chodesh, how about the idea of less than a month
old? Less than a month old is not in the Torah's fixed
values of ערך. It's also you don't do פדיון הבן pidyon haben
yet. And as was interestingly pointed out yesterday, right, the Torah's fixed
value of a בן חודש ben chodesh is five שקל, which is
also the amount of פדיון הבן. pidyon haben. But less than a
month old is not on those charts. So maybe I would say
the same הוה אמינא hava amina in reverse. Somebody that's off of
the Torah's chart is less than a month old, also would I
could not I would not obligate myself if I vowed to pay
the market value. It's not true. Even less than a month old
still has a market value and whatever the market value is for
a five-day-old baby, you go you go look at the slave market,
you determine the market value. So בהדיא קתני לה, behedya katani lah,
that's explicit in the משנה. Mishna. Now it's not in our משנה,
Mishna, but it's in a later משנה. Mishna. So later משנה Mishna
says that you pay דמים, damim, you pay the market value even
for less than a month old. ואי להסגויי עובדי כוכבים, V'ei l'asguyei
ovdei kochavim, how about a non-Jew? Let's say I vowed to pay
the market value of a non-Jew.
So בהדיא קתני לה, behedya katani lah, that's also explicit in a
later משנה, Mishna, right? That's also somebody with a market value. What
do you do? You look at the market value for? Yeah, exactly.
So לעולם L'olam probably the higher market value. I mean that's always
the question, I should say interestingly, when the גמרא Gemara says but
you pay the market value, when you determine somebody's market value,
there's a question in the ראשונים Rishonim whether it means the market
value as they would be sold as a Jewish slave or as
a non-Jewish slave. Clearly the market value as a non-Jewish slave is
higher because a non-Jewish slave is fully owned, a Jewish slave you
have much more limits in terms of how you use them and
also you only own them for like seven years.
So generally it's overwhelmingly assumed that the market value even when you're
valuing a Jew is at the non-Jewish slave because you're trying to
discern give some value to them to some, you know, dollar value
to them as an entire person. So the only market that really
treats people as objects with values is the slave market and as
a non-Jewish slave, that's where they're completely objectified. So anyway, but it
would really wind up being the same. So the גמרא Gemara says
לעולם להסגויי פחות מבן חודש. l'olam l'asguyei pachot miben chodesh. All right,
so when it says everybody is the object of a vow, it's
including less than a month old. So then why didn't we already
say it later? All right, התנא ברישא מפרש HaTanna bereisha mefaresh fine,
here it says it in very general sense and then later it
spells it out more in detail. But Rashi says, one minute, so
Rashi says, of course you could have easily have picked any of
the other ones. You could have picked, you know, the non-Jewish slave
or anything and said התנא ברישא מפרש HaTanna bereisha mefaresh or Rashi
says no, actually we are going to find out that that there's
a debate around issues of less than a month old. There's some
debate, not exactly a straight debate about whether there's value, but there's
some debates around people with less than a month old. So therefore
we wanted to say that the משנה Mishnah here first of all
made a general statement about it, that less than a month old,
even less than a month old, everybody agrees that there is a
value that is paid, and then you'll see more details about that
later on, we'll get into more specific details about that category of
less than a month old. Yes, Michael, question? So it would have
been the same thing if they would have said the value of
a שכיב מרע shachiv mera would be the same thing as מנוול
ומוכה שחין? menaval umukei shechin? Yeah, whatever, if there's a market value,
and if there's not a market value, then there would not be
דמים but there would be ערך, absolutely. I mean there's no categories
when it comes to דמים, there's no categories, it's just whatever the
market determines. Even someone like יוצא ליהרג yotzei l'hehareg or is that
not considered now? So again, if there's, presumably there's very little market
value to those people. Aren't they considered like dead already? Well, that's
an interesting question whether somebody that's like a טרפה treifah or whatever
is categorically excluded. Okay, so we'll worry about those questions later on,
but again, for the issue of דמים, it has very little to
do with predefined halakhic categories, it really has to do with with
what the market determines. The question about ערך has much more to
do with Torah-defined categories. Okay, but we'll see about this as we
continue on in this מסכת. Let's take a look.
Okay, so the גמרא Gemara says like this.
הכל סומכין, Hakol somchin, we get to do a little a little
survey of ש״ס Shas where הכל hakol is used in different משניות.
mishnayot. Okay, so first of all we have a משנה mishnah in
the beginning of חולין Chullin that says everybody does סמיכה. semichah. הכל
סומכין. Hakol somchin. So and it's also in מנחות. Menachot. לאתויי מאי?
L'asuyei mai? What does that come to include? לאתויי יורש, L'asuyei yoresh,
that even an heir, although only owners do סמיכה semichah on their
קרבנות, korbanot, if you bring if somebody let's say you see a
קרבן korban, that got lost and it's wandering around in in ירושלים
Yerushalayim and you bring it because whoever's it is, it's a קרבן,
korban, you don't do סמיכה, semichah, you're not the owner. Only owners
do סמיכה. semichah. What about an heir? Somebody dies and his and
his son brings the קרבן, korban does he do סמיכה? semichah? So
why wouldn't he? Because he's not the owner, he's only the heir.
I understand, he inherited it, so that's exactly the question. He's not
the person that accepted the personal obligation, but to some degree he's
taking his father's place. So that's exactly why it's debated. So we
say it is including an heir, ודלא כרבי יהודה, ud'lo k'Rabbi Yehuda,
not like רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda who says it's excluded. הכל ממירין,
Hakol memirin, everybody can do תמורה. temurah Again, תמורה temurah. is forbidden,
but if you do תמורה temurah. it's effective. And and again, only
the owner can do תמורה. temurah? If I go to Michael's קרבן
korban? and I say this in exchange for that, I didn't transgress
and it did not trans and the קדושה kedushah didn't extend. I've
done nothing because only the owner is in a position to do
תמורה. temurah, What about the heir? Can the heir do תמורה? temurah
It's a similar type of a question. Do you view the heir
as the new owner of the קרבן? korban? So these are obviously
linked concepts. So לאתויי יורש l'asuyei yoresh also to include an heir
does תמורה, temurah. it's effective. ודלא כרבי יהודה. Ud'lo k'Rabbi Yehuda. So
again, not like רבי יהודה. Rabbi Yehuda. So these are linked concepts,
is an heir considered the owner of a קרבן? korban, דתניא, Detanya,
we taught in a ברייתא, beraita, יורש סומך יורש ממימר. Yoresh somech
yoresh memir. An heir can do סמיכה semichah and an heir if
he does תמורה temurah. it is effective. רבי יהודה אומר יורש אינו
סומך יורש אינו ממימר. Rabbi Yehuda omer yoresh eino somech yoresh eino
memir. רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda says an heir does not do סמיכה,
semichah, an heir does not do תמורה. temurah מאי טעמא דרבי יהודה?
Mai ta'ama d'Rabbi Yehuda? What's his reasoning? קרבנו, Korbanov, it says if
a person is by סמיכה semichah it says he should put his
hand על ראש קרבנו, al rosh korbanov, on the head of his
קרבן, korban. ולא קרבן אביו, v'lo korban aviv, and his is meaning
very very much his own personal, even not his even his father's
is excluded. ויליף תחלת הקדש מסוף הקדש. V'yalif techilas hekdesh misof hekdesh.
And he learns an act of sanctifying from the end of the
process. Um the now the beginning of sanctifying is here ironically, somewhat
ironically, the act of תמורה. temurah, It's not really the beginning, the
beginning is when I sanctify the animal, the תמורה temurah is piggybacking
on that, but it still is an act of creating sanctity into
the second animal, whereas the act of סמיכה semichah is after the
sanctity has been created, the end of the process is I do
סמיכה semichah and I שחט. shacht. So רבי יהודה, Rabbi Yehuda, once
we learn that an heir cannot do סמיכה, semichah, we learn the
end of the process, from the beginning of the process, sanctifying at
least in the context of תמורה, temurah. from the end of the
process. מה סוף הקדש, Mah sof hekdesh, the same way the end
of the process סמיכה, semichah, יורש אינו סומך, yoresh eino somech, it's
not the heir, אף תחלת הקדש, af techilas hekdesh, the beginning by
תמורה temurah, which creates קדושה, kedushah, יורש אינו ממימר, yoresh eino memir,
is not in a position to do תמורה. temurah Basically, you are
not considered the owner of this קרבן. רבנן, Rabbanan, and the rabbis
say, ואם המיר ימיר, v'im hamir yamir, if anyone anybody does תמורה,
temurah, תמורה tmura. under any circumstance, so the double language is understood
to be including. לרבות את היורש, L'rabos es hayoresh, to include even
the heir. ויפינו סוף הקדש מתחלת הקדש. V'yapinu sof hekdesh mitechilas hekdesh.
And we do the reverse, we say if you can that whatever's
true at the beginning to create קדושה, kedushah, you're enough of an
owner to do תמורה, tmura you're enough of an owner to also
do
סמיכה. semichah. the same way at the beginning of the process, if
you’re enough of an owner to create תמורה tmura, *temurah*, to instill
קדושה kedushah *kedushah* in the second animal, again although it’s forbidden, אף
סוף הקדש *af sof hekdesh* even at the end by סמיכה smicha?
*smichah* יורש סומך *yoresh someich*. Okay, so basically it is a simple,
it’s a question, right? Somebody inherits property and this is always an
interesting question in הלכה *halacha*, how much is the son or the
heirs considered to be new entities that just have this property transferred
to them? How much are they a continuation? ברא כרעא דאבוה *bra
k'ra d'avuha* is a phrase in הלכה *halacha*, the son is like
the legs of the father. How much are they a continuation of
the father? To what degree is this animal considered their קרבן *korban*
or their father’s קרבן *korban*? Okay, now the גמרא gemara *Gemara* just
plays out the rest of the פסוקים *psukim*, what everybody does with
the other פסוקים *psukim*. רבנן האי קרבנו מאי mai, עביד ליה lei,
*Rabbanan hai korbano mai avid lei*? What do they do with 'his
קרבן *korban*' which רבי יהודה yehuda *Rabbi Yehuda* learns to say not
the קרבן *korban* of an heir, only your own? So, מיבעי ליה
*miba'ei lei* קרבנו ולא קרבן עכו"ם *korbano v'lo korban akum*, not that
of a non-Jew. קרבנו ולא קרבן חבירו *korbano v'lo korban chaveiro*, and
there’s another קרבן *korban* which is only yours and not your friend’s.
Okay, so you can only do it on your own. If I
say to somebody, Michael, bring this קרבן *korban* for me, do me
a favor, you’re going to ירושלים *Yerushalayim*, even if I ask him
to do סמיכה smicha. *smichah* for me, he cannot. It’s not his
קרבן *korban*, it’s mine. You cannot have a שליח *shaliach* do סמיכה
*smichah*. Certainly if I didn’t make him a שליח *shaliach*, but even
if I made him a שליח *shaliach*. What’s the example of a
non-Jew? So you might say non-Jew is the same. I mean, if
I have a non-Jew’s קרבן *korban*, I don’t do סמיכה *smichah*, it’s
not mine. But actually non-Jew excludes two other cases. First of all,
this non-Jew himself brings a קרבן *korban*.
The הלכה *halacha* is that non-Jews can bring קרבנות korbanot, *korbanot* to
the בית המקדש *Beit HaMikdash*, they don’t do סמיכה *smichah*. Of course
that’s not so clear how you exclude that from the phrase קרבנו
*korbano*, right? Because that’s more that’s more excluded from דבר אל בני
ישראל *dabeir el bnei Yisrael*. So תוספות Tosafot *Tosafot* says קרבנו *korbano*
excludes that although the non-Jew doesn’t do סמיכה *smichah*, maybe the כהן
*kohen* would do סמיכה *smichah* in his stead. Okay, and therefore it’s
saying that even that is not done. Okay, so there’s no סמיכה
*smichah* done for
if it’s not yours, whether you’re doing it for a favor for
a friend, whether the non-Jew brings it, the כהן *kohen* should do
for him. No, you do not do סמיכה *smichah* if it is
not your own קרבן *korban* and also a non-Jew does not do
סמיכה *smichah*. Okay, so that’s what’s excluded from קרבנו *korbano*. Now
קרבנו *korbano*, now apparently it says קרבנו *korbano* a third time. There’s
a question exactly in רש"י Rashi *Rashi* and תוספות Tosafot *Tosafot* where’s
the third קרבנו *korbano*, we’re not going to get into it, Michael
can worry about it. But anyway, לרבות lerabot *l'rabot*, so that actually
is considered not to exclude but to include. בעלי חוברין לסמיכה *ba'alei
chovarim l'smichah*. If you have a, if you have a קרבן *korban*
that you’re bringing in שותפות *shutfus*, a group. So five of you
are bringing a קרבן *korban*, we say that the קרבנו *korbano* here,
now you understand why it’s including, because what it’s saying is every
single one of you has to do סמיכה *smichah*. One person cannot
represent the group, each one of you, every person whose קרבן *korban*
it is must do סמיכה *smichah*. Okay, so that’s what we learn
out from קרבנו *korbano*, but not to exclude an heir. What do
you do with פסח *Pesach*? What do you do for men? What?
פסח *Pesach* does not have, you don’t do סמיכה *smichah* on פסח
*Pesach*, do you?
What?
I’m sorry, you have to bring it into the... well no, you
bring it, but it’s a חבורה *chaburah* and there’s like what, five
to the...
yeah, I mean you bring it into the בית המקדש *Beit HaMikdash*,
but I think I don’t think there’s סמיכה *smichah* on a קרבן
פסח *korban Pesach*.
סמיכה *smichah*... trying to remember...
we’ll worry about it when we get to פסחים *Pesachim*, I guess.
What? It probably doesn’t apply to it. It says שה לבית *seh
l'bayit*, yeah, so maybe that would be it. But we don’t limit
it to... no, this doesn’t say where you do סמיכה
*smichah*.
Okay, I’ll get back to you on that.
You don’t do סמיכה *smichah* on everything.
Well, actually you do it on חטאת *chatat*, you do it on
אשמים *ashamim*, you do it on עולה *olah*.
I’ll get back to you on that. Okay, let’s keep on going.
So the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* says like this, okay, רבי יהודה *Rabbi
Yehuda*, רבי יהודה *Rabbi Yehuda* would say לרבות lerabot כל בעלי חוברין
לסמיכה לית ליה *l'rabot kol ba'alei chovarim l'smichah leit lei*. He doesn’t
hold of that. He holds one person, he doesn’t have an extra
קרבנו *korbano*, he uses it to exclude the heir and therefore he
says if it’s a group, it’s not true
that everybody has to do it, one person can do it for
the whole group. ואינהו אית ליה *V'ina is lei*, even if he
holds of that, now at the top of דף ב עמוד ב
*daf b' amud b'*, עכו"ם וחבירו מחד קרא נפקי *akum v'chaveiro m'chad
kra nafkei*. He takes the case of a non-Jew and the friend,
essentially it’s the same point, it’s don’t do it for somebody else.
But it’s not excluding a non-Jew doing it for himself, that’s learned
from a different פסוק pasuk. *pasuk*. So those are really the same
point, it’s don’t do it for somebody else. So he gets it
from one פסוק pasuk *pasuk*. אישתייר ליה תרי *Ishtarei lei trei*. He’s
left over with two קרבנו *korbano*. חד קרבנו ולא קרבן אביו *Chad
korbano v'lo korban aviv*, one to exclude for the father, an heir
does not do סמיכה *smichah*, ואידך לרבות כל בעלי חוברין לסמיכה *v'idach
l'rabot kol ba'alei chovarim l'smichah*. And then he would also, then he
could agree with the Rabbis that if you have a group, every
member of the group has to do סמיכה *smichah*. Okay. For רבי
יהודה *Rabbi Yehuda* האי המיר hamer ימיר מאי mai, עביד ליה *hai
hamir yamir mai avid lei*? What does he do with the double
language of המיר ימיר *hamir yamir* which the Rabbis... learned to say
that an heir can do תמורה tmura and can do סמיכה? So
אמיבעי amibei ליה, he's learned it to tell you לרבות את et
האשה ha'isha that even a woman does תמורה. דתניא, detanya, we taught
in the ברייתא, braita, לפי lefi שכל shekol הענין ha'inyan אינו eino
מדבר medaber אלא ela בלשון bilshon זכר, zachar, the whole פרשה parsha
of תמורה is in the male, of course Tosafot points out the
whole Torah is in the male, okay,
but for some reason here we think that maybe it'll exclude women.
מנין manayin סופנו sofenu לרבות את et האשה, ha'isha, we know we're
going to include women, where do we get that from? תלמוד talmud
לומר lomar המיר ימיר, the double language. ורבנן, verabanan, where do the
Rabbis get it from? ואם, the extra ו vav and if, it
says in the פרשה there. ורבי verabi יהודה ואם לא דריש, darish,
he doesn't make that דרשה. drasha. So Tosafot asks the question, why
all of a sudden do we need something to include women, right,
you know, all of the laws in the Torah are בלשון bilshon
זכר, zachar, we assume women are included. So Tosafot says yeah, but
normally the principle for including women is for example there's a principle
that all of, you know, all of the punishments, you know, are
women are included, or all of the prohibitions, or all of the
positive מצוות mitzvot that time isn't binding, but this is less about
the question about punishment or obligation and so on, it's about the
effect of the act of תמורה, so maybe somehow that wasn't already
covered when we sort of assume that women are always included and
therefore we needed this. But it does raise that question. The idea
that כולה kula תורה כולה kula בלשון bilshon זכר, zachar, you know,
somebody once told me I remember once we had somebody in the
Yeshiva speaking about certain aspects in, you know, in Israeli law, you
know, I forget exactly what the topic was, it might have had
to do generally with issues about protecting battered women or other types
of questions. Anyway, but one of the things that you
realize that the entire, you know, all of the laws in that
were in Israel were basically all in the male. They also assume
the male gender. But there was actually some law that they had
found somewhere or some rule that said that, you know, whenever either
gender is used it's assumed to refer to the other gender. So
since then all the laws she's been introducing have always been in
the female gender.
So but anyway, in the Torah we assume it's all in the
male and as a general rule we assume that it includes both
genders, but it still is always in the male. All right, now
we are done, that's הכל hakol? in areas that relate to קרבנות,
תמורה and סמיכה. Now we spread our net even further and go
beyond those areas. Okay, so let's take a look. הכל hakol חייבין
chayavin בסוכה besukka לאתויי מאי, le'asuyei mai, everybody is obligated in סוכה,
sukka, what does that include? So it's not actually everybody, women are
not obligated, right, people that are sick are not obligated. So who
is being included in the extra הכל? hakol לאתויי le'atuyei קטן katan
שאינו she'eino צריך tzarich לאמו, le'imo, if a child doesn't need his
mother, and the way that the גמרא Gemara says you measure that
is that when he wakes up he doesn't say the first thing
he says is not
mommy mommy, okay, so it's modern I guess. So if he's at
a stage where he doesn't need his mother, then he is obligated
at least in a sense of at least from a חינוך chinuch
perspective. דתנן, detnan, קטן katan שאינו she'eino צריך tzarich לאמו le'imo חייב
chayav בסוכה, besukka, he's obligated in a סוכה. sukka. Now we're going
to talk in a minute, we'll see a lot of things we're
going to do here is minors and when they become obligated as
חינוך chinuch perspective and what exactly is the age, it's not the
same age for all הלכות. halachot. So let's see a couple more
cases and then we'll reflect on this.
הכל hakol חייבין chayavin בלולב, belulav, so we have a משנה mishna
also that everybody's obligated in a לולב. lulav. לאתויי מאי, le'asuyei mai,
what does that include? לאתויי le'atuyei קטן katan היודע hayode'a לנענע, lena'ane'a,
from the time a minor knows how to shake the לולב, lulav,
do the right, you know, do the act correctly. דתנן, detnan, קטן
katan היודע hayode'a לנענע lena'ane'a חייב chayav בלולב. belulav. Once the minor
knows how to shake the לולב, lulav, he's obligated to do it,
at least a Rabbinic obligation of חינוך. chinuch. I should say by
the way that in חינוך chinuch it's a fascinating question the אחרונים
acharonim discuss, who's obligated in חינוך? chinuch? Normally we assume it means
the parents, the father, the mother, there's actually interesting debates there whether
it's just the father or the father and the mother, but חינוך
chinuch normally the obligation we assume is on the parents. The phrase
here is קטן, katan, the minor from the time he knows is
obligated, sounds like it's the minor that's obligated. But you know some
point out that there's obviously a little paradox about that because if
he's not yet at the age that he can be obligated, how
can you obligate him Rabbinically? Like what obligates him if he's excluded
from any sense of obligation? But some still do say that the
way it's phrased is more his obligation, not as the parents, which
is interesting, that's at least the terminology used here. Okay, הכל hakol
חייבין chayavin בציצית betzitzit לאתויי le'atuyei מאי, mai, everybody's obligated in ציצית,
tzitzit, what does that include? לאתויי le'atuyei קטן katan היודע hayode'a להתעטף,
lehit'atef, from the time a minor knows how to wrap himself in
the ציצית. tzitzit. דתניא, detanya, קטן katan היודע hayode'a להתעטף lehit'atef חייב
chayav בציצית, betzitzit, if he knows how to wrap
himself, he's obligated in ציצית. tzitzit. הכל hakol חייבין chayavin בתפילין bitfillin
לאתויי le'atuyei מאי, mai, everybody's obligated in תפילין, tfillin, let me finish
this set and then I'll talk about it.
לאתויי le'atuyei קטן היודע לשמור תפילין, katan hayodeia lishmor tefillin, when the
minor knows how to watch his תפילין. tfillin, דתניא, detanya, meaning protect
it, meaning not bring it into a dirty place, not actually have
passed gas and bodily functions that are inappropriate when one is wearing
תפילין. tfillin. דתניא detanya דתניא D'tanya קטן katan היודע hayode'a לשמור lishmor
תפילין, tfillin. when the time minor knows how to watch his תפילין,
tefillin, אביו לוקח לו תפילין, aviv lokeach lo tefillin, his father has
to buy תפילין tefillin for him. So let me say a couple
things about all these. First of all, an interesting thing to note
is why did it all of a sudden switch to the father?
Why didn't it say when he knows how to be שומר shomer
his תפילין tefillin he's obligated to wear תפילין? tefillin? Why does it
say the father has to purchase תפילין? tefillin? So תוספות Tosafot basically
says well, the קטן katan doesn't have money to purchase... well right,
he says, he says first of all they you know it was
a time when they didn't you don't go out and buy a
בגד beged specifically for ציצית. tzitzit. If you had a בגד beged
that had four corners then you put ציצית tzitzit on it but
you didn't make a point of buying a special ציצית tzitzit בגד.
beged. So you're not buying the actual טלית, tallit, you're just buying
the ציצית, tzitzit, that's a relatively minor purchase. The לולב lulav and
אתרוג, etrog, you know, you can borrow it from your father unless
it's the first day, but anyway תוספות Tosafot assumes that לולב lulav
and אתרוג etrog are relatively inexpensive, certainly compared to תפילין. tefillin. So
there the emphasis was the obligation. But תפילין, tefillin, which is something
that you can't, now why can't you borrow somebody's תפילין? tefillin? So
I think we're also assuming that the general assumption was was that
they used to wear the תפילין tefillin the whole day. So then
you can't borrow somebody's תפילין. tefillin. Everybody needs their own. And also
it's much more expensive. So you have to point out that here
it's not just enough to say the קטן katan is obligated, you
have to tell the father he's got to shell out the money,
which also points to the sense about the father or the parent's
obligation in חינוך. chinuch. So that's just the phrase about אביו לוקח
לו. aviv lokeach lo. Now how about the different ages here? The
general assumption about this is is that the obligation of חינוך chinuch
is a function of when the child is not only physically able
to do the מצוה, mitzvah, but to some degree also like it's
a meaningful sense of an education. A, they can do it properly
and you know and B, somehow they can also relate to what
they're doing. Although here the function is you know more on the
doing it properly, but one imagines part of that also is that
it's not just some rote meaningless act, although it does raise interesting
questions you know about the nature of חינוך. chinuch. To what degree
is the nature of חינוך chinuch just purely habituating and therefore maybe
it even begins even if the person doesn't fully understand what they're
doing as long as they're technically doing it correctly. The emphasis here
is on the technical performance. And therefore what's interesting is what this
reflects about the nature of the מצוה. mitzvah. These statements here, although
they're about the minor's obligation, are often used to prove something about
the nature of the מצוה. mitzvah. For example, by the לולב, lulav,
we normally assume the מצוה mitzvah of לולב lulav is just you
take it. But we all know that after you take it you
do this shaking and you do the shaking during הלל. Hallel. Is
that just some add-on type of a thing or is that actually
conceptually part of the מצוה? mitzvah? The fact that it says you're
not a minor isn't obligated until he can do it indicates that
this is a central part of the מצוה, mitzvah, which is why
for example some ראשונים Rishonim say that even after you've taken it,
if you forgot to make a ברכה, bracha, you can still make
a ברכה bracha before you've shaken it because the shaking is actually
a central part of the מצוה mitzvah of לולב. lulav. Similarly by
the טלית, tallit, the wrapping, you know if you see when somebody
puts on a טלית גדול, tallit gadol, they normally like wrap themselves
with it. This is because according to many many גאונים, Geonim, ראשונים
Rishonim and so on, if a person just wears a four-cornered garment
but it's not a garment that has with it an aspect of
עטיפה, atifah, of wrapping, now exactly what wrapping meant in the old
time, it might have meant something that goes on the head, it
covers the head, it might have meant something that sort of goes
somewhat around the face, but it was not considered a full garment
if it was not something that somehow there was a wrapped aspect
to it. Exactly what the parameters of wrap are are not clear.
So there here as well, if it's somebody that is not in
the category of wearing this garment in that way, even if they
can put it on, it is not somebody who really is that's
not the מצוה mitzvah of ציצית. tzitzit. The מצוה mitzvah of ציצית
tzitzit is only with a garment that is or at least that
can be wrapped. Now the interesting issue is the תפילין. tefillin. When
it says לשמור תפליו, lishmor tefilav, do we understand that that just
means that if he's passing gas it's a you know בזיון bizayon
to the תפילין? tefillin? It's disrespect to the תפילין tefillin and that's
the concern, that could just be it, that's not about the act
of the מצוה. mitzvah. Or do we actually understand that the keeping
the mindset that תפילין tefillin is on you and acting appropriately and
that sense of you know keeping it in mind is actually part
of the מצוה mitzvah of wearing תפילין tefillin itself? And there you
have aspects כי שם ה' נקרא עליך, Ki shem Hashem nikra alecha,
the גמרא Gemara compares the wearing of the תפילין tefillin to the
wearing of the ציצית, tzitzit, that God's name is on you, the
consciousness of it. There even was a sense that you know that
some people would make a ברכה bracha when they took off the
תפילין tefillin of לשמור חוקיו lishmor chukav because it says ושמרת את
החוקה הזאת. V'shamarta et hachukkah hazot. So the aspect of the שמירה
shmirah of the קדושה of תפילין tefillin and the awareness of the
significance of wearing it could very well be a part of the
מצוה. mitzvah. So again, these are fascinating because of what they might
reflect about how we conceptualize what is sort of the act of
the מצוה, mitzvah, which gets back to the case about the קטן
katan and the סוכה. sukkah. Why why there is it a time
that he doesn't need his mother? It could just be a simple
point that women are exempt, so women are in the house, the
men are out in the סוכה. sukkah. If the kid wakes up
and says mommy mommy and the father isn't used to going and
getting him his bottle or whatever you know maybe it's like inappropriate
he should be with his mother, but it's not really in defining
the act of מצוה. mitzvah. But also you could say to the
degree that the מצוה mitzvah of סוכה sukkah is תשבו כעין. teshvu
k'ein. תדורו, taduru, it's a sense of living in a place, so
if somebody is completely dependent on another, they're not actually doing their
own living, they're being sort of more they're more the object somebody
else is sort of placing them somewhere to for a person to
actually say that they are, you know, as a subject living in
a place that requires a certain greater degree of independence. So I
think all of this is very interesting from not just the question
of age, but from the question of how we think about the
act of the מצוה. mitzvah. Just one other question, I mean, we
don't see anyone buying תפילין tefillin for קטנים ketanim that are less
than 13 years old. Right, what happened to that? So what happened
to that is, and the same, and that's a very good point,
you know, we start חינוך chinuch like some people start חינוך chinuch
by ציצית tzitzis from the age of three. We start חינוך chinuch
much earlier, but in the same reason we don't wear תפילין tefillin
the whole day because we say we are not at able to
give them the proper respect and focus and attention and protect our
body from passing gas and other types of things, and therefore we
limit it to only the time that we דאוון. daven. That's how
that's how that's halachically explained. So the same explanation is why we
don't begin the חינוך chinuch of תפילין tefillin except very close to
the בר מצוה bar mitzvah because we don't want to, you know,
sort of, risk putting it in, doing it in a way that
cannot be properly respectful of and a proper קיום kiyum of the
שמירה. shmirah. So essentially here we say, we assume you're not ראוי
ra'uy to be שומר shomer your תפילין tefillin until you actually are
very close to being בר מצוה. bar mitzvah. It's one of these
things that's kind of on the books. What? Well, no, actually here
it makes more sense here, it's actually we're just saying no, it's
when he is ראוי לשמור תפילין. ra'uy lishmor tefillin. It's just nowadays
we assess that that is very that that is a very hard
criteria to satisfy. I read ציצית tzitzis also, yeah. I thought the
רמב"ם Rambam said, I guess what we're saying is you're only really
vividly obligated when you're בר מצוה, bar mitzvah, but you know, there's
always חינוך. chinuch. But you know, but we kind of do it
earlier for חינוך. chinuch. Yeah, that's exactly what this is, it's about
חינוך. chinuch. Okay, הכל חייבין בראיה. hakol chayavin bire'iyah. So those were
all about these more like, you know, daily ritual מצות. mitzvos. Now,
everybody is obligated in ראיה, re'iyah, again, again, not everybody, men. This
is about the מצוה mitzvah of יראה כל זכורך, yeira'eh kol zechurcha,
appearing in the בית המקדש with a קרבן ראיה, korban re'iyah, an
עולת ראיה olas re'iyah on the רגל. regel. So, לאתויי le'atuyei מאי,
what does that include?
לאתויי מי שחצי עבד, le'asuyei mi shechetzi eved, what's הכל hakol? including?
חצי עבד וחצי בן חורין. chetzi eved vechetzi ben chorin. Half slave,
half free. A slave is not obligated because it says לפני האדון
ה', lifnei ha'adon Hashem, the master God. So only somebody who has
no other master, their only master is God. What about somebody who's
חצי בן חורין חצי עבד? chatzi ben chorin chatzi eved? How do
you do that? You're owned by partners, one partner frees you, the
other does not. So to one degree, one aspect of you is
free and that has no other master than God. The other aspect
does. So here we're saying that maybe the הכל hakol is coming
to say that that person, because there's an aspect that's free, is
obligated in
ראיה. re'iyah. ובידרבינא דאמר מי שחצי עבד וחצי בן חורין פטור מן
הראיה, uvid'Ravina de'amar mi shechetzi eved vechetzi ben chorin patur min hare'iyah,
according to Ravina that says that somebody who's חצי עבד וחצי בן
חורין chatzi eved vechetzi ben chorin is exempt. לאתויי, le'atuyei what does
it include? חיגר ביום ראשון ונתפשט ביום שני. chiger beyom rishon venispashet
beyom sheni. So if somebody was a lame, if you are lame
and you cannot walk, so you're exempt because it says רגלים. regalim.
So you have to be able to do it by walking, even
if somebody could bring you there. If somebody was lame, let's say
they were and somehow they healed by the second day, so now
do they bring an עולת ראיה? olas re'iyah? If you could not
have brought it the first day, do you make it up on
the other days? So that's a debate. Okay, so we say the
following. We say, לאתויי חיגר ביום ראשון ונתפשט ביום שני. le'asuyei chiger
beyom rishon venispashet beyom sheni. If he was lame the first day
but he got better the others, he still brings it because now
he is obligated. גמרא Gemara says, הני ניחא למאן דאמר כולן תשלומין
זה לזה. hani nicha leman de'amar kulan tashlumin zeh lazeh. That's good
if you say the other days of יום טוב, Yom Tov, each
day can be a makeup for the previous day. אלא למאן דאמר
כולן תשלומין לראשון, ella leman de'amar kulan tashlumin lerishon, but if they're
only makeups of day one, לאתויי le'asuyei, מאי, what's including? Because here's
the point. You can bring an עולת ראיה olas re'iyah if you
did not bring it on the first day, you can bring it
on any of the remaining days of חול המועד Chol Hamoed and
יום טוב. Yom Tov. But conceptually what are we saying? Are we
saying it's really an obligation of day one and the remaining six
or seven days are makeups for day one? If that's what we're
saying, then if you were exempt on day one, there's no point
about bringing it the other days because it's only a makeup for
day one and day one you weren't obligated. Or do we say
no, it's not only a day one obligation, it's really an everyday
obligation and therefore even if you couldn't have done it on day
one, you can do it on another day. So what is the
idea of הכל? hakol One suggestion is הכל is including somebody who
was exempt on day one. The גמרא gemara says fine, but that
only works if every day is an independent obligation. If they're all
makeups, then that person would also be would still be exempt. So
the גמרא gemara... says so what's it including? לאתויי סומא באחת מעיניו.
le'asuyei suma be'achas mei'einav. If somebody is blind in one eye, so
therefore we're going to see in a minute that if you're fully
blind you're exempt. What would be the story about blind in one
eye? So here we're saying that הכל would come to include that.
ודלא כי האי תנא, udlo ki hai tanna, not like the following
תנא. tanna. דתניא, detanya, we taught in the ברייתא, braisa, who says
even one eye blind
is exempt. We taught in the ברייתא, braisa, יוחנן בן דהבאי אומר,
Yochanan ben Dahavai omer, Yochanan ben Dahavai says, משום רבי יהודה, mishum
Rabbi Yehuda, in the name of Rabbi Yehuda, סומא באחת מעיניו פטור
מן הראיה. suma be'achas mei'einav patur min hare'iyah. If somebody is blind
even in one eye, they're exempt from appearing in the בית המקדש,
שנאמר, shene'emar, the verse
said, יראה. yeira'eh. The same way you're coming to see, you're coming
to to present yourself, to appear. Or it's the same way God
sees you must whatever. Here's the problem with this פסוק. pasuk Okay,
we read the פסוק pasuk a number of times. We read the
פסוק pasuk. שלוש פעמים בשנה יראה כל זכורך את פני אדני ה'.
shalosh pe'amim bashanah yeira'eh kol zechurcha et pnei Adonai Hashem. So יראה
yeira'eh is in passive, shall be seen, all your males shall be
seen. There's a problem. If you read it יראה yeira'eh shall be
seen, the end of the verse should not be את פני אדני
ה'. et pnei Adonai Hashem. את et defines the object of the
verse. It should be יראה כל זכורך לפני
ה' yeira'eh kol zechurcha lifnei Hashem maybe. את פני et pnei is
the object of the verse. So it's clear that the grammar of
the פסוק pasuk should be read יראה כל זכורך את פני ה'.
yeireh kol zechurcha et pnei Hashem. You will see God. But actually
the מסורה masorah probably because of the high anthropomorphism reads it as
יראה. yeira'eh. But the מדרש midrash does not lose sight of the
fact that actually יראה yeireh is a very powerful read of this
פסוק. So on the basis of that we make a דרשה drasha
connecting יראה yeireh to יראה. yeira'eh. And we say that the same
way you appear and are seen by God and God sees you
as it were with God's eyes fully, you have to be able
to see with your two eyes and you have to have full
sight, which really is getting back to the פשט pshat of the
פסוק which is talking about you seeing, not you being seen. Okay.
So therefore כשם שבא keshem sheba מה לראות בשתי
עיניו mah lirot bishtei einav the same way God sees with two
eyes אף לראות בשתי af leira'ot bishtei it's actually funny because the
order is wrong. It should be the same way you are seen
by God fully, you have to see fully. Anyway, that's the point.
ואיבעית אימא, v'iba'it eima, so therefore one thing it could be saying
is to reject that, to say even as long as you have
sight in one eye that is sufficient. You still need sight, you
still need the לראות, lirot, but you don't need it fully, even
one eye is sufficient. What if you have like bad sight in
both eyes? That's not a problem. ואיבעית אימא v'iba'it eima and if
you want you could say לעולם לאתויי מי שחציו עבד וחציו בן
חורין. le'olam l'atuyei mi shechetzyo eved v'chetzyo ben chorin. We'll go back
to half-free half-slave. Ah, we said that not everybody agrees to that.
Some people say half-free half-slave is exempt because you're still partly a
slave. וכי קשיא לך דרבינא, v'chi kashya lach d'Ravina, you were bothered
about רבינא Ravina that רבינא Ravina says that person is exempt. לא
קשיא, lo kashya, not a problem. כאן במשנה ראשונה כאן במשנה אחרונה.
kan b'mishnah rishonah kan b'mishnah acharonah. It's whether it's the early stage,
the first משנה mishnah or the later משנה. mishnah. What does that
mean? It means that there's a general debate about בית הלל בית
שמאי Beit Hillel Beit Shammai how you deal with a half-slave half-free.
And in an early stage we allowed that position to remain half
and half and then you'd be exempt. But at a later stage
we agree that that was an intolerable situation and that person must
be freed. And since that person must be freed, even before they're
freed, they're considered to be essentially free and would therefore have an
obligation of appearing in the בית המקדש. What is this first and
later stage? Now we thought in the משנה, mishnah, מי שחציו עבד
וחציו בן חורין, mi shechetzyo eved v'chetzyo ben chorin, somebody is half-slave
half-free. עובד את רבו יום אחד ואת עצמו יום אחד, oved et
rabo yom echad v'et atzmo yom echad, works for his master one
day and himself one day. דברי בית הלל, divrei Beit Hillel, that's
what בית הלל Beit Hillel says. אמרו להם בית שמאי, amru lahem
Beit Shammai, בית שמאי Beit Shammai said to them, תיקנתם את רבו,
tikantam et rabo, you were very nice to his master, ואת עצמו
לא תיקנתם, v'et atzmo lo tikantam, but you didn't help out this
poor slave. In what way? I mean he does have one day
every other day to himself. Here's the way you didn't help him
out. לישא שפחה אי אפשר, lisha shifchah ee efshar, how about getting
married? He can't marry a slave woman because he's half-free and a
free man is not allowed to marry a slave woman. בת חורין
אי אפשר, bat chorin ee efshar, he can't marry a free woman
because he's half-slave. יבטל, yibatel, so say don't have kids, don't get
married? והלא לא נברא העולם אלא לפריה ורביה, v'halo lo nivra ha'olam
ela l'piryah v'rivyah, the world was created for פרו ורבו, pru u'rvu,
which might be the reason that saying this אלא ela might be
to emphasize how important it is that mandates that we do something
to fix this issue. It also might be saying that even let's
not debate technically whether he's obligated in פריה ורביה piryah v'rivyah and
whether he's an אונס ones or whether you know he has an
obligation as a slave. It doesn't really matter whether there's a technical
מצוה mitzvah of פריה ורביה. piryah v'rivyah. There's a much larger religious
mandate here which is the world was created for this purpose.
שנאמר, shene'emar, as the verse says, לא תהו בראה, lo tohu verahah,
God did not create the world to remain desolate, לשבת יצרה, lashevet
yetzarah, He created it to be settled. So you cannot allow this
situation to continue. But
you allowed it to happen. Unless someone, I understand. Exactly, this should
protect עגונות. agunot. Absolutely.
You needed some, you needed a בית שמאי. Beit Shammai. I mean
that's you know the problem about, yeah, I fully agree with you.
You needed somebody that's going to free עגונות. agunot. Let's free all
the עגונות. agunot. Why not? Well
no, anyway, but I mean no, I mean the point is is
that you certainly had in the גמרא Gemara that the rabbis faced
up, alright, that the rabbis faced up to, right, the גמרא... Gemara
and particularly untenable, right, right, and actually this is the fourth פרק
Perek of גיטין, Gittin, which is that the Rabbis faced up to
untenable situations and they did something about it. That's, and this is
one example, but that's the whole fourth פרק Perek of גיטין, Gittin,
I agree. אלא מפני תקון העולם, Ella mipnei tikkun ha'olam, for the
sake of, this is the פרק in גיטין Gittin that's about תקון
עולם, tikkun olam, about making תקנות takkanot because the situation is untenable.
So for the sake of fixing the world, כופין את רבו ועושה
אותו בן חורין, kofin et rabbo ve'oseh oto ben chorin, you force
the master and you make him free, you force the master to
free him, וכותב שטר על חצי דמיו, vechotev shetar al chatzi damav,
and the slave will owe him the half of his value, fine,
it's an IOU, he'll have to eventually pay it, but you still
have to free him. וחזרו בית הלל להורות כדברי בית שמאי, Vechazru
Beit Hillel lehorot kedivrei Beit Shammai, Beit Hillel reversed themselves, which is
quite fascinating, not only that they reversed themselves, but normally you assume
Beit Hillel are the ones sort of championing the human dimension and
here Beit שמאי Shammai is the one that has this high degree
of sensitivity. Anyway, the way this translates for us is, so הכל
חייבים בראיה hakol chayavim bire'iyah means a half-slave half-free, even if you
normally would say, you would have prior said they're exempt, now that
everybody agrees you force the master to free, everybody agrees that they
are obligated because they are, if they haven't gotten their freedom yet,
they're about to get their freedom, they're obligated to get their freedom,
and that enough makes them considered free that they are obligated in
ראיה. re'iyah. Let's just read one more sentence. הכל חייבים בתקיעת שופר
לאתויי מאי? Hakol chayavim bitkiat shofar le'atuyei mai? Everybody's obligated to blow
the שופר. shofar. It's funny, you would have expected this to have
been quoted earlier when we had all those other ritual מצוות. mitzvot.
It's funny the order that the גמרא Gemara sort of is doing
this in. What does this include? לאתויי קטן שהגיע לחינוך. Le'atuyei katan
shehigia lechinuch. Okay, a minor that's at the stage of חינוך, chinuch,
of education. It's interesting here that it does not give you a
particular age, it just says the generic הגיע לחינוך. higia lechinuch. דתנן,
Detnan, we taught in the משנה, Mishnah, אין מעכבין את הקטן מלתקוע
ביום טוב, ein me'akvin et hakatan miltkoa beyom tov, you do not
prevent a minor from blowing the שופר shofar on יום טוב. Yom
Tov. And actually תוספות Tosafot, says it's not just you don't prevent,
but there's actually another משנה Mishnah that speaks about you do, you
actually blow for minors on יום טוב, Yom Tov, and the way
the גמרא Gemara resolves it is it says that you blow for
them specifically when they are at the age of חינוך. chinuch. Okay,
so again, it's the issue of being at the age of חינוך.
chinuch. Now, what is that age of חינוך? chinuch? So רש"י Rashi
quotes a גמרא Gemara that says eight or nine, nine or ten,
and תוספות says what are you talking about? That's when it comes
to fasting, that you don't start kids fasting when they're younger. But
when it comes to other things, everything is as appropriate for that
מצוה. mitzvah. So if you take a look at the תוספות שהגיע
לחינוך, Tosafot shehigia lechinuch, which we'll just end with that, he quotes
רש"י that says like eight or nine, nine or ten, and then
one line down he says ולא נהירא דהתם בחינוך קטן להתענות קאמר,
velo nehira dehatam bechinuch katan lehit'anot ka'amar, that's about fasting, אבל בשאר
מצוות כל אחד ואחד לפי דרכו, aval bish'ar mitzvot kol echad ve'echad
lefi darko, כדאשכחן לעיל גבי לולב וסוכה ותפילין, kedashkachan le'eil gabei lulav
vesukkah utfillin, everything is measured by its own measure. So why therefore
here didn't it tell us what the measure is by סוכה? sukkah?
Probably
because by שופר shofar is completely passive. Like שופר shofar is you
don't blow, you just hear. So it's harder to measure is he
able to do it. What does that mean, able to do it?
This is blowing on יום טוב, Yom Tov, this is blowing. Yeah,
but it also means blowing for them. Okay, I'm not getting into
all of that, okay? But at least, but to the degree that
it means blowing for them, the question is what does it mean,
are they of the age, right? It's just passive, so therefore it's
more of an abstract question, are they focusing, are they understanding, are
they aware of what's going on? So that's I think harder to
measure and therefore we just leave it at the abstract aspect of
שהגיע לחינוך shehigia lechinuch without defining it as concretely. Michael's question is
a good one, whether it means we let them blow or we
blow for them, that has to do with two contradictory משניות mishnayot
which the גמרא is only here alluding to and not getting into.
Here's an, I understand, but you look at תוספות, he says that
this is only a hint to the larger discussion of this in
the גמרא in ראש השנה. Rosh Hashanah. Okay, so tomorrow we will
continue with the very interesting משנה Mishnah about women reading מגילה Megillah
for tomorrow.